<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the primary visitation of the Most Reverend Father in God Michael Lord Arch-Bishop of Armagh, primate and metropolitan of all Ireland, and lord high chancellor of the same. Held at Drogheda, August 20. 1679. / by Rich. Tenison ...</title>
            <author>Tenison, Richard, 1640?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184950</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097949</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2576:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the primary visitation of the Most Reverend Father in God Michael Lord Arch-Bishop of Armagh, primate and metropolitan of all Ireland, and lord high chancellor of the same. Held at Drogheda, August 20. 1679. / by Rich. Tenison ...</title>
                  <author>Tenison, Richard, 1640?-1705.</author>
                  <author>Boyle, Michael, 1609?-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Took and John Crook, printers to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, and are to be sold at His Majesties Printing-House in Skinner-Row.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴, E².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Ireland --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, --  II, 17. --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Church and state in Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Primary Viſitation OF THE Moſt Reverend FATHER in GOD MICHAEL Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>ARMAGH,</hi> PRIMATE and METROPOLITAN OF ALL IRELAND, AND Lord High Chancellor of the Same.</p>
            <p>Held at <hi>Drogheda, Auguſt</hi> 20. 1679.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICH. TENISON,</hi> Dean of <hi>Clogher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Took</hi> and <hi>John Crook,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and are to be ſold at His Majeſties Printing-Houſe in <hi>Skinner-Row.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171525:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171525:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>Michael,</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> Primate and Metropolitan of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Lord High Chancellor of the ſame.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO great and high are your Graces zealous Affections, and juſt Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for the beſt of Kings, that no Sermon which is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to Allegiance can paſs unregarded by you, but receives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement beyond its merit; of which obſerved truth, your Commands for this mean Diſcourſe are an evident Demonſtration. I little thought, having ſo happily eſcaped your learned Ear, to undergo the Teſt of your moſt piercing Eye: but having then preached Obedience to others, I muſt practiſe it my ſelf, and ſubmit to the kind Injunctions of ſo great a Superior; 'tis therefore laid at your Graces feet, hoping my Loyalty will attone its many imperfections, and the dayly fears of our Soveraigns Aſſaſſination may juſtifie its zeal and warmth; For, what tongue can be ſilent, to ſee the Father of our Countrey aſſaulted with ſuch variety of Deaths? To ſee the Ponyard at his ſacred Breaſt, the fatal Doſe preparing, and the Gun ready to fire, muſt fill every true Subject with horrour and reſolution. He is the Head of the Body Politick, and as in the Natural, all the Members ſtrive to defend the Head, and ſhare in its pain, ſo ſhould it be in this; the bloody hand which is lift up againſt him muſt wound all loyal ſouls, the curſed Sword which ſtrikes at him muſt pierce their hearts; they muſt value the Life of their Prince infinitely above their own, and run through the greateſt difficulties to preſerve him; and if they dye in his defence, they perpetuate their Name on Earth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reward of their Fidelity in Heaven; which true Proteſtant Principle made many thouſands in the late times leap into the midſt of dangers, and run through the armed Troops of their too potent Enemies; their greateſt force could not make them yield, but they covered that Poſt with their Bodies, which they could not maintain with their Arms, and willingly died martyrs for their King, their Religion, and Country.</p>
            <p>This (my Lord) many places can witneſs, but none more in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom than this Loyal Town, in defence of which, your Graces valiant Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171525:3"/>(famous for Courage and Conduct) and many hundreds more, did triumphantly loſe their lives; their blood ran in ſtreams through our ſtreets, and like the brave <hi>Leonidas</hi> in the Straits of <hi>Thermopyle,</hi> they with a ſmall number oppoſed an Army, and no doubt but there are vaſt multitudes in each of theſe Kingdoms, who will imitate thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick ſpirits, and cheerfully fall, for the King, and the Church.</p>
            <p>And if ever good Subjects ſhould demonſtrate their Courage, it is now; if ever Proteſtants ſhould love, honour and obey their King, it is now; when the cruel Jeſuits are plotting and conſulting to murther him, and ſubvert our Religion; in this they are cloſely combined, this they hold lawful and juſt, as I have proved out of many of their Books, beſides <hi>Mariana,</hi> (though a Jeſuit lately executed would confeſs none elſe of that Judgment.) But alas! inſtead of uniting againſt them, we ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into Sects and Factions; we run into Schiſms and Diviſions, and make way for them to deſtroy us; we forget how the Civil Diſcords of our Anceſtours brought our King and Countrey under the Subjection of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, and I wiſh our violent heats about Religion, do not at laſt bring our Church under the vaſſalage of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, and our State into ſome imminent danger; for without an agreement in that, our Kingdoms cannot flouriſh: Where men differ in Eccleſiaſticks, they uſually claſh in Politicks, and have their own intrigues and deſigns to promote their Opinions; they are jealous and doubtful one of another, and like the ſeveral Factions in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Carthage,</hi> while they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the good of the Commonwealth, they deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>Of this, our late bloody and tragical Devaſtations are an undeniable Evidence, and that we are falling into the ſame miſeries again, is more than probable; for ſeditious and fiery ſpirits do now (as formerly) fill the floating heads of the vulgar, with cauſleſs fears and jealouſies, and make the King and his greateſt Miniſters the common Subject of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and if all things be not done, and timed according to their humour, (as if they knew all Reaſons of State, and had Intelligence from all parts of the world) then do they calumniate and ſlander the Government; and aſperſe thoſe moſt, who have ever been moſt eminent for their Loyalty to the King and the Church, and would now die in their defence; and thus are the people deluded, and made ſubſervient to ſome aſpiring male-contents, who by their Agents and Emiſſaries do in all places reflect on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171525:3"/>the Management of Affairs, and make them Patrons of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who have ever abhorred it, and were lately for their aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to it to be cruelly murthered, as is conſtantly affirmed by<note n="*" place="margin">Dr <hi>Oats</hi>'s Nar. p. 16. 23, 25.</note> thoſe on whoſe Evidence moſt of our late Diſcoveries depend.</p>
            <p>But your Grace well remembers, this was their method in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our late troubles, they (according to <hi>Machiavals</hi> Advice) did boldly libel and calumniate, and to deſtroy both Church and State, they ſubverted their ſtrongeſt Pillars, under the pretence of being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and rotten with Popery, and by clamour and noiſe made all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who were not as raſh, furious, and diſloyal as themſelves. Nay thoſe holy Prelates, whoſe moſt learned Works will be eternal Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and moſt impregnable Fortreſſes againſt the whole power of <hi>Rome,</hi> were moſt unjuſtly and ingratefully branded with the ſame Character; and ſuch are now their Deſigns and Practices; They would perſwade the people to have an ill opinion of our Governours, that they might the more ſecurely carry on their own Deſigns; But I hope God will infuſe a ſpirit of Diſcerning into our King, our Parliaments, and Counſellors, and that all who are in any Authority will fix one Eye on thoſe ſubtile <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderminers both of Church and State, that while they are moſt zealous and intent (and bleſſed be God they are ſo) on the ſuppreſſion of Popery, our rigid Sectaries may not grow too numerous and formidable; for when greedy and voracious flames ſeize on both ends of a Ship, the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle part is like to periſh; and we know Diſeaſes long neglected may prove deſtructive. In the beginning of the Reformation, the <hi>Genevian</hi> Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did ſpread it ſelf, and the good Queen could not eaſily prevent it, her Thoughts being chiefly employed in the Extirpation of Popery, which dangerous Evil the wiſe King <hi>James</hi> did ſoon perceive, and reſolve to redreſs, as appears by his Proclamations againſt them, and his firſt Speech to his Parliament, in which, ſpeaking of the Sectaries and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliſts, he ſays, They are ever diſcontented with the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and impatient to ſuffer any Superiority, which makes their Sect unable to be ſuffered in any well governed Commonwealth; yet he did not do it; for the <hi>Gunpowder Plot</hi> turned his Eyes wholly on the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and ſo had the Separatiſts an opportunity to increaſe to ſuch: prodigious number, as proved deſtructive to his Son, the Church, and theſe Kingdoms: Which, with the two late Rebellions in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171525:4"/>may move our Governours to look back ſometimes, and watch the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Kirk:</hi> But I preſume too far; and muſt beg your Graces pardon, for the loſs of your minutes in viewing this rude Addreſs, ſo low a Style is no way fit for your Graces view, who are (as was ſaid of <hi>Clem. Alex,) Inter Doctos, ſummè Eloquens, inter Eloquentes, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè Doctus;</hi> In you the Piety and Zeal, the Wiſdom and Courage, and other juſtly admired Accompliſhments of your Graces late great Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, are moſt happily met; You every way fill and adorn your Chair, in which, that your Grace may long ſit, and continue what you are, one of the greateſt Pillars both of Church and State, is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe your Grace, Your Graces moſt Humble and Obedient Servant,</hi> RICH. TENISON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171525:4"/>
            <head>1 Pet. 2.17. <hi>Honour the King.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AMong the Plots and Conſpiracies of the Conclave and the Conſiſtory, amidſt the unjuſt Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, and the Presbyterian Kirk, to a Superiority over Monarchs; This A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Canon may not unſeaſonably be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed on; for when the Papiſts have (beſides all their former bloody Treaſons) now lately contrived the Murther of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, and our diſloyal Separatiſts in <hi>Scotland</hi> have run again into Rebellion, and publiſhed a trayterous Declaration, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Supremacy, and calling his Government an Uſurping Power (though their own Chronicles witneſs him to be the Hundred and Tenth King of his Line;) 'tis high time for all Orthodox and Loyal Clergy men to declare their Deteſtation and Abhorrency of ſuch unchriſtian Tenets and Practices, which are ſo directly oppoſite to this Injunction of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Succeſſours, the Popes deſire and glory to be eſteemed, and whoſe peculiar Followers, our fiery Zealots, do no leſs proudly boaſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall quote him againſt them, and from him prove them great Enemies to Princes, and Invaders of the Rights of Kings; for in this Epiſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> he more than once commands Obedience to be given unto them, and that in moſt general terms, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ut oſtendat, non Qualitates Perſonarum, ſed Officium hic reſpici debere.</hi> Magiſtracy, whether in Jew or Gentile, Chriſtian or Infidel, was then to be regarded; none did preſume to abſolve Subjects from their Allegiance; neither was Dominion then founded in Grace, nor the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of Kings to be judged by the People; but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the preceptive Will of God, the very Throne and Seat of Judicature, did exact Obedience. Which, leaſt they being Chriſtians, ſhould refuſe the Pagan Monarch, who then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171525:5"/>reigned, who was ſo cruel and outragious againſt them; leaſt they ſhould fail in their Duty to him, deny to pay him Tribute as other ſubjects did, or take up Arms in defence of their Lives, he twice minds them of their Allegiance, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es them to ſubmit unto him, and all his Prefects, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, in their ſeveral Provinces, and not only and barely to ſubmit to live peaceably and quietly under him; but, which was more, to honour him, <hi>Honour the King;</hi> in diſcourſing of which, I ſhall ſhew,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The meaning of the words, the Duty which ariſes from them, and wherein it conſiſts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Who are the great Violators of it, and their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Pretences.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Who are the beſt Obſervers of it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the beſt Chriſtians, and the trueſt Subjects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The meaning of the Words, and the Duty, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honor eſt clara cum laude Notitia,</hi> or <hi>Teſtificatio de Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiâ;</hi> 'tis that eſteem and reſpect, which is paid to a man in regard of the Place he is in, or the Excellency he is endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with; 'tis a deſerved Fame, Advancement and Exaltation above others, an Acknowledgment of their worth and merit, and a ſuitable Reverence and Obſervance paid unto it. By the King is underſtood the Emperour, and all his Lieutenants, and Vicegerents; ſo that he requires them to give all due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and veneration to the Supream Magiſtrate; and to all who were in Authority under him, to ſhew them all juſt honour and regard in the Obſervation of their Laws, and the payment of their Tribute, <hi>Imperatori ſummos exhibete honores quos capit humana natura.</hi> Gro. <hi>Obſervatione Legum, &amp; Proe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatione Tributorum.</hi> Eſti.</p>
            <p>And the Prince, to whom this duty was to be paid, was that <hi>Portentum hominis,</hi> as <hi>Suetonius</hi> calls him, the inhuman <hi>Nero,</hi> who thirſted after their Blood, and put them to the moſt exquiſite Torments he could invent; for he wrapt them in the skins of beaſts, and let the dogs devour them, he burnt them in pitched coats, and made them ſerve for Torches in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171525:5"/>the night. Even to him was this great Honour to be given, and the Primitive Fathers do largely witneſs, all his Cruelty did never make them fail therein.</p>
            <p>From which you may ſoon note, That it is the Duty of all Subjects to honour the King, be he good or Evil.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had Almighty God made <hi>Moſes</hi> his Vicegerent, and ſetled him in the Government of his People, but he made Laws for them to walk by, and wrote them in Tables of Stone, to denote their perpetuity and duration: and no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had he ſecured his own Worſhip in the firſt Table, but he fixes Honour and Obedience to Magiſtrates in the front of the ſecond, and made it the firſt of thoſe Laws which relate to humane Society; becauſe a man can't perform Acts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to his Inferiours and Equals, who is unnatural and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to his Superiours. And for the ſame reaſon, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws are the Crimes againſt Magiſtrates, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Puniſhments firſt reckoned up, it being impoſſible for any to be good Members of a Commonwealth, who do not firſt learn and practice Obedience to Governours. The Laws will never be well obſerved, where men don't honour the Magiſtrate; Fear may make us go, but its the true Honour we have for our Superiours, which adds wings to our loyal inclinations, and makes us cheerfully perform their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. The word is very comprehenſive, and takes in all that Loyalty and Fidelity, that Reverence and Duty, which we owe to thoſe above us, and by conſequence, ſhews them their Duty to us; ſo that this ſhort Precept is the great Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gament of human Society, and the very Foundation of all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; for while we reſerve that honour for the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate which we owe him, we won't violate his Laws, which are the grand Security of our Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>And it being duly obſerved, it will be the Princes and the Peoples Safety, it will be the guard and continuance of Polity and Government in the World, and will keep Order and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity among us; ſome muſt be exalted above others, and their Injunctions muſt be obeyed, otherwiſe all would tumble
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171525:6"/>into Anarchy and Confuſion. The ſtrongeſt Arm and the longeſt Sword would decide all Controverſies, and we ſhould ſoon devour one another, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Chriſ.</hi> This the Law of God does not only declare, but the Laws of Nature dictate it to all mankind. Men are rational and ſociable Creatures, they can't live like Brutes in Woods and Deſarts. They muſt enter into Communities, Societies and Bodies, for Comfort, Converſe and Safety. And when they are thus convened and gathered, all cannot Govern; ſo that of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity there muſt be ſome Head to guide and rule them, to whoſe Deciſion and Determination all Differences and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts (which will unavoidably happen among Numbers) muſt be referred and ſubmitted. To which having once conſented, they are no longer <hi>Sui Juris,</hi> the Liberty, Authority and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which before they had by Nature, is devolved upon the Magiſtrate, and Him muſt they afterward Honour and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey.</p>
            <p>And thus all Nations and Countreys have their Kings, or other Magiſtrates, to whom they pay Homage and Fealty, and mutual Relations of Superiority and Subjection are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved among thoſe, who are only influenced by the Light of Nature.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Auſt.</note> 
               <hi>Generale pactum eſt Societatis humanae Regibus obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire.</hi> Which Law of Nature, and general Cuſtome in all parts of the world, God has not altered or abrogated, but moſt ſtrongly ratified and confirmed; for both in the Old and New Teſtament we have many ſtrict Precepts for Honour and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Magiſtrates, that ſo that Polity and Order which God and Nature hath eſtabliſhed in the world may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the Magiſtrates, who defend us in our lives, may have that Love and Honour, Obedience and Maintenance; which, for their great and reſtleſs Cares, their vaſt Troubles and conſtant Hazards, are juſtly due unto them. All which grateful Returns are here included in the word Honour; and ſo it is often taken in Scripture; and in that notion ſhall I now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it in reference to the King, and ſhew you how you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171525:6"/>are obliged to love and honour him, to own his Supremacy and obey his Laws, to pay him Tribute and maintain him. In theſe does this Duty conſiſt, from which none born in his Dominions can pretend any immunity or exemption.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We muſt love and honour him.</p>
            <p>Every man who would truly honour the King, muſt firſt love him at the higheſt rate he can, and then all Duty and Veneration will ſoon follow; for if once the Affections be vanquiſhed with any object, they preſently open, and all the Faculties of the Soul are imployed in their Service, all other things are leſs valued and eſteemed, nothing offenſive or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to it is committed; but the Mind is changed and ſquared to the will and pleaſure of that which has overcome them. Theſe are ſome of the effects and influences of true Love: and if we would perform the ſeveral branches of our Duty to the King, as we ought, we muſt firſt very highly love him; which that we may do, let us look on him as the publick Father and Protector of our Countrey, who guards us from forraign Invaſions, and domeſtick Rebellions; by whom Peace is preſerved, Traffique and Commerce increaſe, the Kingdom grows rich and flouriſh, and every man ſits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Vine, and Fig-tree; His coercive Power reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the outrages of the Wicked, and ſecuring our Lives, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Property from the encroachments of Eccleſiaſtical and Secular Robbers; which great Advantages may well move us to love him, and make us willingly give all poſſible demonſtrations of the greatneſs of our Affections, in a full and perfect Obedience to his Commands, expoſing our ſelves to the greateſt hazard to defend his Perſon, and in all our words and actions paying him the moſt ſubmiſſive Regard.</p>
            <p>And then will our Honour for him be the effect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant of our Love, which will ſoon be heightened and exalted, if we conſider him, as one, whom God hath made his immediate Vicegerent, and given him Power and Authority over his People, he hath placed him in the higheſt Seat of Renown, and he hath put a Sword in his hand, to protect
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171525:7"/>and correct his Subjects, and under both temporal and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Penalties hath enjoyned them to obey him. Nay ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous is he of their Honour, that he takes all Contempts and Inſurrections againſt them, as done to himſelf, and hath inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably united our Fear to him and his Repreſentatives; it being impoſſible to fear him, without honouring thoſe whom he hath ſubſtituted in his place. The Apoſtle here ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.21.</note> to make it the more obſervable; and <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo unites them, <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> We muſt then be faſtned to him with the firmeſt chains of Affection, and next to the Deity, whom he perſonates, have the higheſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for him; a loyal ſympathy muſt dwell in us, our Pulſe muſt keep time with his, and we muſt ſhare in the ſickneſs and health, in the joys and ſorrows, the ſafety and danger of our Soveraign; the leaſt injury that is done to him (our Head) muſt affect the whole Body, and we muſt not ſuffer a word that tends in the leaſt to his diſhonour, but to our utmoſt, ſeek to juſtifie his Government, extenuate his Failings; and endear him all we can to the People, which is now moſt neceſſary; there being too many of the Gnoſtick humour, who leſſen the Virtues of their Rulers, and rob them of their juſt Honours,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10.</note> who, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities, nor tremble when they rayl at Glories;</hi> for ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifies.</p>
            <p>A preſumptuous ſort of men, who deſpiſe Dominion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt the Government, and inſinuate an evil Opinion of it into the vulgar, which is a forerunner of Rebellion, ſuch Swellings riſing uſually before breakings out, in the Body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, as well as the natural. And undoubtedly, they who are more ready to queſtion and diſpute the Commands of their Prince, than to obey them, who are ſtill inquiring into the Grounds and Reaſons of publick Actions; and, as far as they dare, do gueſs and deſcant upon them; who call every ſlip a fall, and upon all occaſions inhance the Failings of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, want only ſtrength and opportunity to do more. By
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171525:7"/>the Eruptions of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> we ſee what is within them; he who is a Rebel in his tongue, is certainly ſo in his heart; for out of the abundance of that the mouth ſpeaketh; he that ſtrikes at the King, in his Honour, would have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for his Perſon.</p>
            <p>It muſt be the care then of every good Subject, to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe ſecret and helliſh Engineers, who thus undermine the Throne; and, by falſe and aggravating ſuggeſtions, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the People to riſe up againſt the Lords anointed, towards whom not only our words, but our very thoughts are reſtrain'd, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. We muſt demonſtrate our Honour for him in our juſt repreſentation of his Actions to the People, and diſſwade them from the Itch of prying into State Affairs, and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Actions of Princes, and their faithful Miniſters; they are beyond our Ken, and we can't judg rightly of them; weak and falſe Opticks may fancy every molehill a mountain, and the ignorant will think Stars fall, when they only ſhoot, or glance: ſoon may our Senſes be deceived, when we look at inadequate Objects, and at too great a diſtance.</p>
            <p>Perſwade we men then, to move Regularly in their own ſpheres, to mind their own buſineſs, and not to judg of thoſe above them; and let us never, without juſt indignation and reproof, hear the leaſt Reflection on our Governours: 'Tis not generous to hear thoſe we love, ill ſpoken of, and 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, and diſloyal, to ſuffer the leaſt Paſquil againſt our Prince, the common Parent of our Countrey; we ſhould vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate him, and his Subſtitutes from all factious and ſeditious Aſperſions, and ſuffer none <hi>to revile the Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>nor curſe the Rulers of our People,</hi> but always ſhew the greatneſs of our Love to them, in being zealous for their Honour, in raiſing them all we can in the Eſteem of the World, and cheerfully paying all Tribute and Taxes; which is another Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of our Honour to them, and next to be diſcourſed on.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Praeſtatio Tributorum,</hi> or Maintenance, is contained in the word Honour; and all who pretend Honour for the King,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171525:8"/>muſt willingly perform it; 'Tis the ſignification of the word 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>The Elders that rule well, be accounted worthy of double Honour; i.e.</hi> Eſteem and Maintenance; alluding to the Elder Brothers Portion which was double;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deutr.</hi> 21.17.</note> Princes then muſt be ſupported by their Subjects, Tribute and Cuſtom muſt be conſcienciouſly paid unto them, for which you have Chriſts Command and Example, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. where he orders them not to give, but to render or reſtore unto the King his Taxes; not as Gift, but as Debt, as the juſt Reward of that Protection, and Safety, which we have from him; and ſo 'tis explained and confirmed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.6. And ſo obſervant was Chriſt in it, that he wrought a Miracle to perform it: and <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> declare the great readineſs of the Primitive Chriſtians to pay Tribute in the midſt of all their Perſecutions. And if you reflect on the great Care, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude, which continually attend the Throne; the vaſt and unavoidable Expences which muſt ſupport its Glory; the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Dangers, and private Aſſaſſinations, which they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, and their Readineſs to hazard their Royall Perſons in your defence; you can't, without the greateſt violations of duty and gratitude, deny your proportion of Taxes: Their whole life is full of trouble, and their days are ſpent in miſery; like the Lamp, to give light to others they waſt themſelves; They ſtand in ſlippery places, and the Throne is covered with Ice; their Crown is ſurrounded with Thorns, and has often proved ſo very ponderous, and uneaſy, that many of our own, and Forraign Princes have groaned under its inſupportable preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; the Conſervation of their Fame at home and abroad, their watching the Actions and Deſigns of all neighbouring States, and the ballancing or ſuppreſſing the Factions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of their own aſpiring, covetous, and unruly Subjects, give them but few quiet and refreſhing ſlumbers. Nay, in the greateſt confluence of Enjoyments, when they have been ſated with Victories; ſo troubleſome have their very Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels been, that they have deſerted their Thrones, longing for a quiet Retirement, and ſecure Obſcurity; and ſome have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171525:8"/>complained, they never had one days eaſe, after their Heads were incircled with the Royal Diadem. In a word, they ſpend their whole life in conſulting our good; and let us therefore pay Tribute to maintain them, their inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and Armies, by whoſe care and vigilancy we ſleep in ſafety, and let us honour them moſt, who bear the greateſt ſhare in the Troubles of Government, and are moſt aſſiſting to the King. To raiſe great Sums when the ſupport of his Grandeur, and the Kingdoms Honour require it, is but a juſt ſign of our Gratitude and Loyalty unto him, and let the next be, our Obedience to all his lawful Commands, for that alſo is included in the word Honour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt ſhew our Honour to the King in obeying him.</p>
            <p>The Law of God, and the Law of Nature, and the Laws of all Nations, give Kings Supremacy, and Authority over their native Subjects; and without a manifeſt breach of thoſe, we cannot reſiſt their lawful Commands. And ſuch all are to be eſteemed, which do not plainly thwart, and poſitively contradict, the revealed Law of God; for if the thing which the Magiſtrate requires, be undetermined by the Law of God, and indifferent in it ſelf, his Command in ſuch caſes muſt be binding to us, and obtain our Obedience: as for inſtance, Reaſon, and the Cuſtom of all places ſhews, there muſt be a Determination of Circumſtances in every Society, otherwiſe there will be nothing but Confuſion. Now if the deciſion of theſe, be not plain in Scripture, the Governours, who have the Charge over us, may do it, to promote Regularity, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of time and place in the Worſhip of God, according to the Apoſtles Canon, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to Command, or Appointment; <hi>Res ordinatim in Eccleſiâ faciendae,</hi> is Mr: <hi>Cartwrights</hi> own gloſs upon it. In matters both real and ritual, ſubſtantial and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Decency and Order is to be obſerved; and when they have determined ſuch Circumſtances, and Ceremonies, in Gods Service, as are not contrary to Scripture, nor forbidden by it; but are harmleſs in themſelves, and undecided by the Law
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171525:9"/>of God, we ought to obſerve them. The very Commands of lawful Magiſtrates take away the indifferency, and require a Conformity and Obſervance under ſin: They conclude, and limit our choice, and it is ſin in us, not to obey them, when they are indifferent. Nay, if what they enjoyn be doubtful, their Command ſhould weigh down our private Opinion, till we are cleerly convinced of the Sinfulneſs of what they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and then, and not before, muſt we diſobey them. <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num dat qui jubet dare, ejus vero nulla culpa eſt, cui parere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt.</hi> The Laws of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and other Nations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the Perſon who obeyed the Magiſtrate, from all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or trouble of Law; and ſo St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſtates it in the caſe of the Souldier,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. 22.</hi> c. <hi>74.</hi> Con. Fauſ.</note> who is not certain, whether what he is ordered to do, be againſt the Law of God or no. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe reum faciat Regem iniquitas imperandi, innocentem verò militem oſtendat Ordo ſerviendi.</hi> The Magiſtrate may offend in commanding, but not he who obeys; the <hi>Principium acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis</hi> is in him, and he muſt anſwer for it. Thus ſhould we behave our ſelves, when what is commanded, is only doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or indifferent, we ſhould have meekneſs of Judgment, complying and condeſcending Spirits; we ſhould diſtruſt and reject our private humours, and fancies, for the general quiet of the Kingdom; and by our Conformity to the Rules impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhew our Honour to the King, and never reſiſt them, unleſs they be clearly againſt the revealed Law of God.</p>
            <p>In ſuch caſe only have we liberty to deny, but even then, we muſt refuſe it with all humility, and meekneſs, patiently undergo Impriſonment or Death, but never uſe any open reſiſtance; and thus have all Nations underſtood the Power, and Prerogative of Princes; for were there Decrees to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with Force and Violence, no Order or Government could be in the World: And therefore the very Heathens ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe Subjects to dye,<note place="margin">Tacit:</note> rather than lift up a hand againſt their King, though he were Tyrannical, and did exact unlawful things. The Gods have given Princes Power to govern, and nothing is left to the Subject, but the Glory of Obedience;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171525:9"/>let them be what they will, we muſt obey without reſiſtance. Many are the Laws, and moſt ſevere were the Puniſhments, which they ordained, to defend the Majeſty and Grandeur of their Kings, their Prefects, and Officers; if the Souldier broke the Stick, with which the Centurion ſtruck him, he was put to death.</p>
            <p>This Nature taught them, and there is natural Allegiance due from every Subject, to the Prince of the Country where he is born, though that Prince did not make him ſwear; he tranſgreſſes the Law of Nature, if he denies Fealty to him; and whether ever he is ſworn or no, he is bound to be true to his native Prince; for the Fidelity of Subjects, proceeds ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally from the Law of Nature, which is eternal, and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable, and not from the obligation of Oaths; and he vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates this Law, who doth not pay all Honour and Subjection to that Prince, in whoſe Country he his born and reſides, though he never took Oath of Allegiance or Supremacy.</p>
            <p>But if my King require an Oath from me, to aſſure him of my Fidelity, I muſt take it; and I am guilty of Perjury, as well as Diſloyalty, if I ever ſwerve the leaſt tittle from it. He is the Head of the Society, or Community, of which I am a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: to him, before my Oath, I owed homage by nature; and no Power under Heaven can diſcharge me from that natural Allegiance, which I owe him, nor abſolve me from the Oath I have taken, without his conſent.</p>
            <p>Beſide all which, the Law of God has in many places en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned Obedience to Kings; and there are not more poſitive and plainer Commands for any Duty, than for Honour, Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and Obedience to Princes; and we find no perſons exempted from it, but both Clergy and Laity are ſubject to it, as I ſhall fully prove by Scripture, and Antiquity: and all who derogate from the Honour of their native Prince, who leſſen his Authority, and deny his Supremacy, act quite contrary to this Text, and in ſo doing, are neither good Chriſtians, nor good Subjects: But they who walk exactly according to this Rule, who honour the King, and no way entrench upon his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171525:10"/>but ſupport it in its juſt height and exaltation, they are the beſt Chriſtians, and the trueſt Subjects, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ought to receive all Countenance, Incouragement, and Protection from Princes; and ſo I haſt to the next thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who are the great Violaters of this Text, and their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Pretences.</p>
            <p>They who chiefly oppoſe the true Proteſtant Doctrine of Obedience to Secular Princes, are the Papiſts, and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts; in this they agree, and their Principles are very deſtructive to Government, quite contrary to the Practice of the Primitive Chriſtians, and the indiſpenſable Rules of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; for the Law of God requireth all perſons to obey their Kings; if St. <hi>Peters</hi> words can have any influence on the Papiſts, I need but name my Text, which has no limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it, but is directed to all men, not imagining his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors would have pretended the contrary; but if they won't be concluded by him in this, and other Texts, let them hear what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the higher Powers;</hi> if every ſoul muſt be ſubject, the Pope and the Clergy are included, and all are there commanded to obey, under the dreadful penalty of Damnation.</p>
            <p>But the Popes have ſince, through Ambition and Avarice, uſurped a Power over Princes; and the Jeſuits, the great Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Papal Throne, have wrote much in defence of it; though they can't but know, that the Popes themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this Rule for many hundreds of years, and all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, both of the Eaſt and Weſt, did exactly conform unto it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. 5.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in Aux.</note> 
               <hi>Repugnare non novi, dolere potero; potero flere, potero gemere, lachrymae meae arma ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> ſays St. <hi>Amb.</hi> They claimed no Authority over them, and made no reſiſtance, but with their Prayers, and Tears. <hi>Cum nefanda perpetimur, ne verbo quidem reluctamur, ſed Deo remittimus ultionem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſays, Obedience to Magiſtrates was the univerſal Doctrine of the Church; the antient Councils, and Synods, were called by the Emperours; the Titles of their Acts are, <hi>Sacra Synodus juxta religioſiſſimorum Chriſtianiſſimor úmque Imperatorum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171525:10"/>Praeſcriptum coacta. Sacra Synodus juxta piiſſimorum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum Imperatorum Decretum per Dei gratia m congregata.</hi> Sometimes the Acts run, <hi>Ex Juſſu, Ex Evocatione, Ex Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione, Regum noſtrorum, &amp;c.</hi> They met by the Emperours Order, Appointment, and Writs;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Cone. Conſt.</note> as they acknowledge in their Letters to them; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and their Acts were made Authentick by their Confirmation.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops humble Addreſſes to the Emperours for Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing their Canons, and Decres; and their Ratifications and Orders for Obedience to them, are frequently recorded; and all the Clergy of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as other places, obſerved their Edicts; and no news then of the Popes Supremacy, as is confeſs'd by the Biſhops, who met at <hi>Bononia,</hi> to ſettle the Church in the time of <hi>Julius</hi> the Third; which Power did all along, both under the Law, and the Goſpel, belong unto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. If you look in the Old Teſtament, you'l find, they had power over the Clergy, from the firſt ſettlement of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt Gods own People; <hi>Aaron</hi> obeyed <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was King in <hi>Jeſurum;</hi> &amp; in the 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 23.21. You ſee both Clergy and Laity entring into a Covenant of Allegiance to young King <hi>Joaſh;</hi> and then did Kings puniſh ſpiritual perſons, as well as others, <hi>Abiathar</hi> was removed from the high Prieſthood by King <hi>Solomon;</hi> and <hi>Joſiah, Jehoſhophat,</hi> and other Kings, did reform Religion, and baniſh Idolatry: and in the New Teſtament, Chriſt and his Apoſtles were all obedient to the Heathen Emperours, paid them Tribute, and owned their Authority, in appealing to them from inferior Juriſdictions. And long after them, The Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were ſo far from having Supremacy over Kings, that other Biſhops would not yield to their Uſurpation; for <hi>Ann.</hi> 325, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> called the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> the four Patriarkſhips were ſetled by the Suffrage of 318 Biſhops, and then it was decreed, that the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſhould have as much Authority in his Patriarkſhip, as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had in his; only the firſt Place was allowed him in General Councils, he being Biſhop of the Imperial City. The Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (in which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171525:11"/>were 150 Biſhops, and which was called by the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi>) granted only a Primacy of Order to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and no more; and <hi>Ann.</hi> 434, the Council of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> (which was ſummoned by the Emperours Order, as the Acts do often ſhew) which was honoured with the preſence of 200 Prelates, ordered, no Biſhop ſhould uſurp any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but what was always his: And about eighteen years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when 430 Mitred Heads did adorn the great Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> they declared, that though the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop had the Precedency of Place, yet was the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> equal to him in all things.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Peters</hi> Charter was not then urged, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church, and I will give unto thee the Keys of Heaven;</hi> they knew, no more was meant by the words, than that, as <hi>Peters</hi> Name ſignified a Rock, ſuch ſhould he be, ſtrong and ſolid, in the building of the Church; and that nothing ſhould prevail againſt the Faith he then had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſſed, ſo <hi>Chryſoſ. Hil.</hi> and <hi>Cypr.</hi> underſtood it, and ſo did St. <hi>Bernard</hi> long enough after them; for he loudly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighs againſt the Tyranny of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, and ſays to <hi>Eugenius,</hi> who was Pope about 1145, <hi>Quid vos alienos fines invaditis? diſce, tibi ſarculo opus eſſe, non Sceptro;</hi> he denies St. <hi>Peters</hi> Charter, and ſays, <hi>Eſto ut quacunque aliâ ratione hoc tibi vindices, non tamen Apoſtolico jure, nec illud dare tibi Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus potuit, quod non habuit.</hi> He thought a Sheephook did bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become that great Shepherds hand, than a Scepter; and that <hi>Peter</hi> could not conſign that power to others, which was never granted to him: and as to the power of the Keys, Chriſt gave it equally to all the Apoſtles, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21. He did not then give it, but according to his promiſe <hi>(I will)</hi> he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward imparted it unto them; ſo that 'tis clear, <hi>Peter</hi> had no perſonal Authority from Chriſt over the reſt of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, neither did he arrogate the Name of Univerſal Biſhop, as Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf declares, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 76; and much leſs ſhould his Succeſſours claim that Title. His Age and Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty might give him a Primacy of Order, but more we do not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171525:11"/>find, And therefore the Priority of place, was all that the firſt General Councils would allow to the following Biſhops of that See, and that only, becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> was the Seat of the Empire; and when the Emperour removed to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo</hi> or <hi>Ravenna,</hi> the Biſhops of thoſe Places did contend with him for ſuperiority; Neither would the Biſhops of <hi>Carthage, Alexandria, Millain,</hi> and other Places, yeild any thing more to <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſaid they were equall in their ſeveral Precincts. The Greek and <hi>Roman Patriarcks,</hi> and Archbiſhops, governed their own Provinces, without Uſurping upon each other; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Diviſion of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> they were quietly ſetled in the Principle City of each Province; where the <hi>Roman</hi> Preſident lived, there did the Chriſtian Metropolitan dwell; the Biſhops were Placed in their ſeveral Dioceſſes, and were ſubordinate to their own Metropolitan, and no other.</p>
            <p>This was the true State of the Church then, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had no Supremacy over Forraign Biſhops, much leſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Kings, but gave both that honour which was due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And thus did it continue till about 606; when <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the Third, and ſixty ſixth Biſhop of that See (according to the beſt Chronologers) uſurped the Title of chief of the Biſhops, by the help of the cruel <hi>Phocas;</hi> for <hi>Sabianus</hi> his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor had it not, and <hi>Gregory,</hi> who was juſt before him, did ſharply exclaime againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who then began to aſſume it; he called it <hi>Nomen Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 4. Epis: 76.</note> and in his 83 <hi>Epiſ. In iſto ſceleſto Vocabulo, nihil eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud quàm fidem perdere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the judgment of that good Pope weighed little with his ſucceſſours, they Triumphed in that ſwelling Title; But tho they dealt thus injuriouſly with their Brethren the Biſhops, (to which ſome near them were ſoon drawn to conſent, but others in <hi>Africk</hi> and <hi>Cappadocia</hi> would not hear of it, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely rebuked them for their Pride) they themſelves did meekly Submit to the Authority of the Emperours,<note place="margin">De. Concil. L. 3. C. 6.</note> who did then and long after convocate and Diſſolve Synods, And as Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus</hi> himſelf confeſſes, did in Perſon, or by their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171525:12"/>Deputies, preſide in Eight General Councills, which they could not have done, had the Pope been then Head of the Church.</p>
            <p>They diſpoſed of ſpiritual preferments, and judged &amp; made Laws in Eccleſiaſtical affaires, one was made by <hi>Honorius,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the very Election of the Pope,<note place="margin">Gratian Diſt. 63. C. 23.</note> &amp; what Edicts they decreed, <hi>Damaſus</hi> and other Popes made be read in all the Churches of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſee the decree for the Conſecration of <hi>Leo</hi> the 8. and the Council, which gave <hi>Jus et poteſtatem eligendi pontificem,</hi> to Charles the Great, when he had ſecured and ſetled the weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Empire; which power his ſucceſſours held, till the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who confirmed the Election of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7.<note place="margin">C. 16.17.</note> but was afterwards excommunicated by him; There alſo will you find that the Pope durſt not Conſecrate <hi>Colonus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Emperours licence; There was no oppoſing them in any thing then, the very time and place for holding Councils were aſcertained by them. You find Pope <hi>Leo</hi> with weeping Eyes begging <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to have a Council in <hi>Italy,</hi> which he refuſed,<note place="margin">Epiſ. 24.</note> and kept at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and Commanded him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it; and in all Places, the Biſhops then obeyed the Princes they lived under, and did not pretend the Popes ſupremacy to defend them; they thought it a ſin (as the ſixth Council of <hi>Toledo</hi> declares it) to queſtion his Power, to whom God hath given Authority over all, but did every where patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what they inflicted upon them, How ſilently did <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Samoſatena,</hi> go into baniſhment at the Emperours command? and did not St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> do the like at the Injunction of the Proconſul of <hi>Affrick?</hi> was not St. <hi>Cyril</hi> impriſoned by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> junior, and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> baniſhed by <hi>Arcadius?</hi> and many more by other Emperours? what need I inſiſt longer on this? the greateſts Biſhops and Fathers of the Church, did throughout the world, ſubmit to their Kings, and gave them all imaginable Honour and Reverence.</p>
            <p>This they did till <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eight about 1295 advanced the <hi>Papal</hi> Grandeur, and claimed Authority over Princes, and by degrees, and with difficulty, he and his ſucceſſors obtained it Generally beyond Seas. In which yon may obſerve the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171525:12"/>of the Popes; firſt they did exact Superiority over the Biſhops, and then over Kings; To aſcend the Throne they pull down the Mitre; In which method they were lately followed by the aſpiring Separatiſts of theſe nations; but neither abroad nor here, could Princes be brought under, till the Biſhops were firſt caſt down: whence by forraign and domeſtick Experience, we may conclude, that Aphoriſm of King <hi>James</hi> will be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally true; No Biſhop, No King. They who rob the Biſhops of their honour will next fly at the Kings; If they once get the Rich Stones out of <hi>Aarons</hi> Ephod, the Jewells of the Crown will be thought too Splendid; If they get the Crozier in one hand, they will be impatient, till they hold the Scepter in the other.</p>
            <p>Thus did the Pope, Thus did the <hi>Kirk;</hi> But though the Pope did exalt himſelf above many forraign Princes, our Kings would not ſubmit to ſuch Uſurpation; moſt of them before and ſince the Conqueſt oppoſed it, and his <hi>Nuncio's</hi> and <hi>Legats,</hi> have been often rejected, and his Bulls and Breves vilified and contemned; his Supremacy denied, the Clergy conſenting thereunto, and Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> moſt ſtrictly Prohibited &amp; forbdiden, of which our ancient and modern Hiſtorians, give many inſtances, too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious now to mention. Do but conſult the Acts of Parliament made in the Reigns of <hi>Edw:</hi> the 1ſt. <hi>Rich:</hi> the 2d. &amp; <hi>Edw:</hi> the 3d. &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, and you'l find, they unanimouſly declared, that the King of <hi>England</hi> ought not to anſwer before any Judge Eccleſiaſtical or Secular, and that the Crown of <hi>England</hi> was ſubject to none but to God, and ought not to be ſubmitted to the Pope, and that he was to exerciſe no Jurisdiction in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Anno</hi> 601 <hi>Dionothus,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Bangor,</hi> proved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> owed no ſubjection to the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> and as <hi>Bede</hi> aſſures you, <hi>Neque precibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 2. C. 2. Ecles. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>neque hortamentis, neque increpationibus Auguſtini, &amp;c.</hi> They would by no means recede from their own ancient Cuſtoms, and traditions, they would not at all ſubmit to what he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor own him for their Arch-Biſhop, tho he came from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171525:13"/>the Pope; the Abbot owned they had love and ſervice for the Pope; and for every true and pious Chriſtian, but he knew no other obedience to be due unto him, whom they called the Pope; Neither was he Father of Fathers, and moreover they were under the Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of <hi>Caerleon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Britains</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> would not in thoſe early times own the Pope for an Infallible judge, tho he ſent Preachers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; they conſulted him as a Patriarch, but no more, and did not follow the Rites of the Roman Church, till the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt; They were ſubject to their own King, and he only ſubject to the King of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and memorable are the words of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> to <hi>Greg.</hi> the 7th; I neither have nor will own Fealty to you, neither do I find that my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors did ever doe it to yours, which is fully made out by the Sages of our Law.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>Scotland,</hi> have anciently done the like, as is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident from their Hiſtorians; and by the advice of their Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops and Clergy, they prohibited Legats from Rome to enter the Kingdom. And in this Country, Fealty was ſworn by the Clergy and Laity at <hi>Liſmore</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. He convened a Synod at <hi>Caſhel;</hi> and there, and at another General meeting of the Clergy at <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> was the Kings Soveraignty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and the conformity of this Church with that of <hi>England,</hi> in all divine offices, agreed on; and in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eights time, they did not only unanimouſly by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but particularly under their hands, to the then Lord Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, renounce the <hi>Papal</hi> juriſdiction; and then did all the Biſhops, of <hi>England</hi> but one, take the Oath of the Kings Supremacy; The Convocation, which is a National Council, conſented to it; and they gave under their hands, that the Pope had no Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in <hi>England;</hi> Nay <hi>Q. Mary</hi> her ſelf commanded the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> not to come into <hi>England.</hi> Thus did theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, both of old and of late, diſown the Popes power, tho they were all then of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all which, the Scripture, Councils, &amp; Fathers ſay, the Pope has no authority over Princes, yet has he uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171525:13"/>it, &amp; their Subjects, who would not ſubmit unto him have been abſolved from their Allegiance, and inſtigated by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries to Rebell; and Kings have been Excommunicated, depoſed, and Murthered, and none has violated this Canon of St. <hi>Peters,</hi> more then his pretended ſucceſſors. I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>P. Zachary,</hi> who depoſed <hi>Childerick,</hi> and Ordered <hi>Pipin,</hi> the Kings high Steward, to Govern <hi>France.</hi> In the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of <hi>Greg.</hi> the 7th. and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 2d. you'l find the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Son urged to Rebell againſt his Father; the Biſhop of <hi>Leige</hi> excommunicated, and he and his Clergy commanded to be put to death, for not renouncing their fidelity, but giving that honour which this Text injoyns to their Native Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign. You know <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> urged the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to Rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our own <hi>Queen E.</hi> And the Divines of <hi>Salamanca</hi> and <hi>Valadolid</hi> incouraged the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to riſe up againſt her; and <hi>Gauran</hi> their Primate was killed in the head of the Rebels, tho I now find him enrolled, with many other ſuch Subjects, among the Martyrs of this Nation, in the Tripartite Epitome of their Modern <hi>Saints;</hi> who had many contrivances to deſtroy that good <hi>Queen.</hi> The like practices they had in the Reigne of <hi>K. J.</hi> and how much they contributed to the Ruine of the late King; and how zealouſly they have of late attempted the deſtruction of this, is obvious to all: their Clergy being the Chief Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries to all theſe Villanies.</p>
            <p>And that which is moſt lamentable is,<note place="margin">John Gavan alias Gawen lately Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> all theſe Miſchiefs proceed from the Principles of their Religion, for theſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been Juſtified by many of their beſt writers, and greateſt Jeſuits; On which allow me to enlarge a little, ſeeing one, who was lately executed for the Plot, did (out of zeal to his order, and knowing how apt the words of dying men are to melt and Influence the too Credulous vulgar) openly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly deny it; 'tis ſtrange he could remember but one of his Brethren, who allowed of that Doctrine, when many of their books run that way. <hi>Becanus</hi> will not ſuffer us to queſtion the Lawfulneſs of Killing refractory and diſobedient Princes,<note place="margin">Angl. Cont. <hi>1.15.</hi> p.</note> if the Pope ſo Order it; And <hi>Leſſius</hi> thought it ſurely, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171525:14"/>of the Church, when he ſays 'tis heretical not to believe the Popes power of depoſing. Indeed <hi>Emmanuel Sa</hi> wont have the King killed,<note place="margin">Voce, Tyran.</note> till he be Excommunicated, but then <hi>(latâ ſententiâ)</hi> any one may be his Executioner; And <hi>Suares</hi> ſays, Tis lawfull to Reſiſt and kill your own King,<note place="margin">L. 6. c. 3 6.</note> if you cant defend your ſelves otherwiſe from his violence; and in another place, he ſays, ſuch inſurrections are no Treaſon, but a Juſt war; which Doctrine was defended by Dr. <hi>Petit,</hi> upon the Murther of the Duke of <hi>Orleance. Simanca</hi> ſays an heretical Prince muſt not only loſe his Kingdom, but his Children ſhall be debarred from the ſucceſſion;<note place="margin">L. Dict. Philop. ſec. 2. p. 1.9.</note> And <hi>Creſwel</hi> affirms, That if any King deſert the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, all Divines and Canoniſts agree, that by the Law of God &amp; Man, he immediatly looſes all power and dignity, before the Pope give Sentence againſt him; his ſubjects are free from all Oaths of Allegiance which they have taken, and they may, and ought, if they have ſtrength, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him as an Apoſtat Heretick; And ſays he, This is the moſt certain, Definit, and undoubted opinion of the moſt learned men.<note place="margin">L. 6. de Reg. p. 59.</note> 
               <hi>Mariana</hi> ſays, The King muſt be admoniſhed to own the Popes Supremacy, but if he wont, they may kill him, how highly does he (and ſo does the Jeſuit <hi>Ribadeneira</hi> alſo) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and extoll that inhuman Monk, who murthered <hi>H. 3d.</hi> and calls that horrid wickedneſs,<note place="margin">C. 6.</note> an admirable greatneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and an Act not to be forgotten, by which he had raiſed to himſelf a great and mighty name; There does he Juſtify the Killing of Kings, for the alteration of Religion, and in the next chapter, directs the manner, how he would have them poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; which very Book was approved of, by their General the Viſitor, and other Grave and Learned men of the Jeſuitical order. It were endleſs to name all who maintaine this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; read <hi>Amphitheatrum Bonarſii,</hi> and the Book <hi>De Abdicatione H.</hi> 3, and you'l find the aſſaſſinating of Kings, largly juſtified; and in <hi>Franciſcus Veronas</hi> Apology for the wicked <hi>Chaſtel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars. 2. c. 2.</note> you'l ſee the Killing of Kings Vindicated with this Circumſtance, <hi>Non obſtante decreto ſupradicti Concilij Conſtantienſis, Privatis, et Singulis licitum ſit, Reges et Principes Haereſeos, &amp; Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171525:14"/>condemnatos occidere;</hi> Tho the Council of Conſtance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed the Contrary, yet may any Private man kill Kings and Princes condemned for Hereſy and Tyranny. <hi>Gretzer, Burgoin, Andreas Eudemons</hi> Apology for Father <hi>Garnet,</hi> and many more, too tedious now to mention, are full of ſuch diſcourſes;<note place="margin">De. Pontif. Rom.</note>; Their great oracle <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cryes out, <hi>Papa poteſt mutare Regna &amp; uni auferre, atque alteri conferre, &amp;c.</hi> The Pope, as he is ſupream ſpiritual Prince, may take a Kingdom from one, and give it to another; and in another place he ſays,<note place="margin">C. 7</note>, if the King be Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical or Heretical, all agree, that he may, and ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and pretends the Primitive Chriſtians would have ſerved them ſo, but that they wanted ſtrength; though he well knew they abhorred ſuch Doctrines, when they were equal to their Adverſaries, as is fully evident from <hi>St. Cypr. Tert.</hi> St. <hi>Aug.</hi> and others; which great Truth is confeſſed by <hi>Barclay</hi> and <hi>Tolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and other of their writers; They own, it was not for want of ſtrength, the Chriſtians did not Rebell, but out of obedience to the Principles of their Religion.</p>
            <p>But that Cardinals judgment prevayled more than all the Primitive Fathers, he affirms, all agree in it; and who will contradict him, ſeeing one Pope ſays, <hi>Non eos Homicidas ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitramur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Urb. 2: Reſcrip. de Occiſ. Excom. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>quos adverſus Excommunicatos zelo Catholicae Matris ardentes, eorum quoslibet trucidâſſe Contigerit;</hi> That good Pope counted them no Murtherers, who out of zeal to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, would kill thoſe whom ſhe Excomunicated. Who will doubt this to be the Doctrine of the Roman Church, when the infallible head thereof (as they call him) gives ſuch great encouragement to ſlay all who are under that ſentence, or ſees another Pope grant a <hi>Jubile</hi> to all Chriſtendom for the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre of <hi>Paris,</hi> or reads the Oration, which his Holineſs made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Murther of <hi>H.</hi> 3d, which is atteſted by Father <hi>Warming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sixt. Quint.</note> who writ and diſtributed the copies among the Cardinalls, to ſecond which, <hi>Guinard</hi> made a Book in praiſe of the <hi>Monk</hi> who did it; and in it adviſed the like to be done to his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, which <hi>Ravaillac</hi> performed, and was alſo juſtified in their Publick writings; and the Doctrine of Depoſing Princes is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171525:15"/>fully aſſerted in many other books dedicaed to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the greateſt Cardinals, and the Superiors of their Orders, carrying their Approbation and Licence in the Front; and not only particular perſons,<note place="margin">Conc. Lat. <hi>4.</hi> Can. <hi>3.</hi> Tom. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> but above a thouſand of their Clergy at once, inveſted the Pope with the Power of Excommunicating and Depoſing ſuch Princes, as at any time ſhould refuſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Hereticks. And did not another Council ratifie the Depoſing of <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">Conc. Lugd. T. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth? and their Doctors tell us plainly, what may be done with them, when the Pope has deprived them, for which I might quote <hi>Creſwell</hi> and <hi>Windeck,</hi> and others, who ſay, that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are bound in Conſcience, and by the Command of God, to expel their Heretical Princes, and that they hazard their Souls if they don't do it; and that all Hereticks ſhould be put to death; they ſhould be burnt or cut in pieces.</p>
            <p>By which you ſee, 'tis not the opinion of one, but of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the Practice of their greateſt Church-men hath been agreeable to this Doctrine; I could name ſeveral of their Biſhops, who, in this Kingdom, turned their Mitres into Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, and their Croziers into Swords, and embrued their hands in the blood of the Kings good Subjects; and who can tell when they will be of a better mind, and more merciful diſpoſition? for their Jeſuit <hi>Campian</hi> ſays, <hi>He would have all know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Eccl. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>1583.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that their Society, which is ſpread over all the world, has made a League, a holy and ſolemn Oath, that while any one of them is alive, they will go on in uſing all ways, to extirpate and root out Proteſtants; and that they will purſue the Ruine of our Princes Perſon, Religion, and Kingdom;</hi> and we have found his words true hitherto.<note place="margin">Becan. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> Comp. Contr.</note> And another of his Brethren ſays, <hi>A Catholick Prince ought not to ſuffer a Heretick to live in his Dominions, unleſs they be too numerous and ſtrong for him; or unleſs he fears ſome Heretical Prince will invade him for it.</hi> And in the preceding Chapter, he ſays, <hi>Hereticks do more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Chriſtian Peace, than Murtherers or Thieves; but they may juſtly be put to death, much more may Hereticks:</hi> In order to which, theſe Kingdoms were formerly given to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171525:15"/>by the Pope, and the Grant afterwards ratified to his Son <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip;</hi> and the Natives of this Country were told in Bulls, and Breves, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ought to be as much oppoſed, as the <hi>Turks;</hi> they were promiſed Victory, and the ſame Rewards, which they ſhould have had, in a Holy War, againſt <hi>Saracens:</hi> And was not a Plenary Indulgence and Pardon of Sins grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eighth to all, who would joyn in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? I could name other Jeſuits, and Popes, who are of theſe bloody Principles; but I fear, I am already irregular in this long Collection, which is extorted from me by the late Jeſuit's forgetfulneſs at his death; who, out of politick Charity to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet untryed, and to prevent Scandal, could think of none that held this Opinion but <hi>Mariana.</hi> And now do you judge what ſort of Religion this is, which allows and enjoyns ſuch open violations of the Laws of God and Nature, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciles Treaſon to the fith, and Murther to the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, which ſaints Men for Rebellion, and damns them for Allegiance; ſuch Tenets are ſurely ſcandalous to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, moſt dangerous and deſtructive to Princes, and highly againſt this Text; and have and will much hinder the Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpel, in Infidel and Pagan Countries, where the Light of Nature, the Practice and Tradition of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and the moral Inſtructions of their Prieſts, teach men to be more Humane, and Loyal, than are many Votaries of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>And would to God, I could accuſe no others for the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of my Text; but alas! O grief and ſhame to ſpeak it! Is not this Doctrine countenanced by many Bigots of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and our neighboring Kirk, who would manacle our free-born Princes, invade their Prerogative, and ſtrip them of thoſe Honours, which their Royal Anceſtors have always enjoyed? who would reduce theſe three Kingdoms into a Seigniory, and make our Imperial Crown as narrow as the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> his Cap: They would allow the King a kind of Regal, but dependant, Authority; He ſhould have the Robes of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Monarch, but nothing of his antient Power: and in ſhort,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171525:16"/>if their Inſtructions were followed, he ſhould be only a Noble Servant to the People, whom they might call to an account, and puniſh when they pleaſe: For, does not <hi>Buchanan</hi> ſay, the People may give the Crown to whom they will? that if Princes do not excel in virtue,<note place="margin">De Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, Reg.</note> they are not to be deemed Kings, but ſhould want the benefit of all humane Society; and if they wont walk according to the Laws made by the People, they are Enemies to God and Man, and ſhould be reckoned among Wolves, and other deſtructive Beaſts; he would have the People carry them into ſome remote parts, or drown them in the Sea, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did their Monſters; he ſays, <hi>Major pars Populi de Magiſtratu judicare, &amp; judices ei for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re queat, aut ſi Trib. plebis Romani, &amp; Ephori Lacedemonii ad leviendam vim imperii queſiti ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> which ſurely he took from <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſtit, l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> ſ. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> who ſays, <hi>If there be popular Magiſirates, to moderate the unrulineſs of Kings, ſuch as the Ephori were to the</hi> Lacedemonian <hi>Kings, the Tribunes to the</hi> Roman <hi>Conſuls, or the Demarchi to the</hi> Athenian <hi>Senate,</hi> (which Power, it may be, the three Eſtates have in every Kingdom) <hi>they are perfidious if they connive at them;</hi> which very words <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> uſed, when he condemned our late gracious Soveraign; or from <hi>Beza,</hi> who affirms,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>24</hi> Epſi.</note> that <hi>Inferiour Magiſtrates are bound to protect the People from domeſtick Tyrants;</hi> or from <hi>Bucanus de Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> who ſpeaks much to the ſame purpoſe; but he far exceeds them all, in moſt ſubtle and bitter inſtigations, to rebel againſt the King; and tells them, how ſome have been perpetually impriſoned, and others baniſhed, and the Actors not cenſur'd for it, and inſtanceth in <hi>James</hi> the Third, whoſe Death (ſays he) was not revenged: but here he forgot, what horrour of Conſcience ſeized on his Son, whom they forced with them into the Field, that he lamented it all his life after, and wore an Iron Chain about him, in token of his great, grief and ſorrow of heart: And how remarkably God puniſhed him, his Nobles, and Commons, at the Battel of <hi>Flowden,</hi> where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe Parricides, or their Children, were ſignally van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, and deſtroyed, as their-own Books witneſs.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171525:16"/>
            <p> He runs on in that rebellious ſtrain, and commends <hi>Thebe</hi> for killing her Husband; <hi>Timolean</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Caſſius</hi> his Son; and <hi>Fulvius</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi> for murthering their Sons and near Kinſmen, for conſulting how to reſtore the Emperour; and ſays, Honours and Rewards were given by many of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Cities, to the Killers of Tyranical Princes; and blames <hi>Domitius Corbulo,</hi> for not depoſing <hi>Nero,</hi> when he might, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His whole Book is full of ſuch traiterous Incentives, and is indeed the Quiver, whence ſhowrs of barbed and empoyſoned Arrows have been ſhot at Monarchs, by all the Pamphleteers in the late times, which makes me quote him ſo largely.</p>
            <p>Thus did he honour the King, in broaching ſuch rebellious Principles among his Subjects, in which <hi>Knox, Cartwright,</hi> and <hi>Goodman,</hi> three of their great Writers, do exactly agree with him in them; &amp; many more are the Jeſuits Principles aſſerted; If <hi>Bell:</hi> ſays the Eccleſiaſtical Eſtate is higher than the Civil,<note place="margin">L. de Cler. <hi>28. See</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers<hi>'s</hi> Preface to the <hi>39</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. <hi>See</hi> Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrights Reply to the ſame purpoſe.</note> Mr. <hi>Travers</hi> will ſay of the Presbyterian Diſcipline, <hi>Omnes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Menarchas, &amp;c.</hi> all the Monarchs of the earth ought to ſubmit their Scepters to it; I might ſhew you the like agreement between the Jeſuit <hi>Parſons</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> between <hi>Emmanuel Sa,</hi> Mr. <hi>Melvil,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibſon,</hi> and many others: but I offend your Ears in naming ſo many; like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> they go hand in hand, to deſtroy the Lords Anointed, though they differ in other points, and they joyntly violate my Text.</p>
            <p>The moſt learned of them declined the Judgment and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of K. <hi>James,</hi> and affirmed, that what was ſpoken in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, ought firſt to be tryed by the Presbytery; and that neither he, nor his Council might meddle with it, <hi>in primâ inſtantiâ,</hi> though the Words were treaſonable: they have called him Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter in their Sermons, ſaid, he was poſſeſt with a Devil,<note place="margin">Spotſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods Hiſt.</note> and made the people riſe up againſt him; neither the Holineſs of the Place, nor the Sacredneſs of his Perſon, could protect him from their rebellious Invectives: But leaſt ſome think, theſe were private and particular perſons, and what they did, ought not to reflect on the whole Kirk; pray obſerve, that their general Aſſemblies, and Synods, have denied the Regal Power:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171525:17"/>And although, in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> in <hi>Geneva</hi> it ſelf, Councils and Synods are ſtill called by the Permiſſion and Licenſe of the chief Magiſtrate, yet would the Kirk convene Aſſemblies, and make Acts of the higheſt Conſequence, contrary to the Kings expreſs Commands. And when he would have diſſolved them, they have proclaimed openly, that their Aſſembly was the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Judicatory, in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and that it was their antient Grievance, that his Majeſty took upon him ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Authority; and therefore they inſtigated the Commons to rebel: for, to give him power in Spirituals, was to erect a Popedom in his Perſon. Nay, in the year 1582, when K. <hi>James</hi> did,<note place="margin">Aſſ. at St. And.</note> by his Royal Letter, by expreſs Meſſengers, by his Maſter of Requeſts, and Herald at Arms, prohibit their Aſſembly, they ſlighted all, and did proceed; then, and afterward, they would allow of no Appeals to the King, but puniſhed thoſe who did ſo,<note place="margin">Print. <hi>47.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Syn.</note> though <hi>Paul</hi> was permitted to appeal unto <hi>Ceſar.</hi> In their Theorems, they ſay, no Power on earth can challenge Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or Dominion upon the Church; but that all Eſtates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that Realm,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Book Diſc. <hi>7.</hi> Head.</note> as well Rulers as others, muſt be ſubject to the Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee; the moſt learned of their Writers, their moſt admired Preachers, their General Aſſemblies, which are the Repreſentative Body of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> rob the King of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authority which belong to him, diminiſh his Power, and with the Pope raiſe themſelves above all that is called God, which the Apoſtle makes a Mark of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and they juſtly urge it ſo againſt him; but what will they ſay, if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort it upon the <hi>Kirk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Bork. Diſc. C. 12.</note> ſeeing they ſay, their juriſdiction is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent, and that all men as well Magiſtrates as others are ſubject to their Judgment? What dos the <hi>Pope</hi> ſay more? They both have depoſed Princes for not owning this Doctrine and by theſe fiery Principles, have ſet the world in a flame. How miſerable then are thoſe <hi>Monarchs,</hi> whoſe Crown &amp; life depend on the pleaſure of ſuch men? <hi>What Proteſtant King and Country can be long quiet where they are?</hi> All our late Troubles ſprung from theſe ſanguinary Doctrines; they ruined both Church
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171525:17"/>&amp; State, &amp; made theſe three Kingdoms one great <hi>Akeldama;</hi> &amp; while there is the ſame cauſe, may we not fear the ſame effects? What has either party Printed, in deteſtation of theſe ungodly Tenets &amp; Practices, which may awaken the Government, to fixt their Eyes upon both? for tho their Heads look ſeveral ways, like thoſe of a <hi>Spread Eagle,</hi> yet are they united in heart, &amp; with their ſharp Claws are ſtill graſping, to pull down the moſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Church under Heaven. Let them for ſhame renounce theſe Rebellious opinions, &amp; be no longer the great violators of this Apoſtalical Canon; let them become good Chriſtians and good Subjects, and unite themſelves to the true old Proteſtants, who are free from the blood of Kings, who have ever been the beſt obſervers of this Text; and conſequently the beſt Subjects; which is the laſt thing to be diſcourſed on.<note place="margin">3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>
               </note> And very juſtly may I call them the beſt Subjects, it being againſt the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of our Church, any way to diſhonour the King; ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns obedience to him, in ſpiritual, as well as temporal things, and gives him the ſame authority which Godly Kings had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews, and Chriſtian Emperours in the primitive Church; her Liturgy, her Homilies, her Canons, her Articles do all own his Supremacy, while both Papiſts and Fanaticks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, pretend a Superiority over him, and that by Divine right.</p>
            <p>Where, by the way, I may note the great Partiality and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of our Separatiſts; who, when they exalted their new Diſcipline above all other Forms of Church Government, call it the Scepter of Chriſts Kingdom, and exact obedience from all Monarchs to it; enter into a rebellious Covenant to defend it, and murther thouſands who oppoſed it; even then did they cry out againſt Epiſcopacy, as intolerable, intrenching on the Kings Prerogative, and taking away his Power; becauſe ſome had learnedly defended the Order to be Apoſtolical &amp; Divine. How great was this Injuſtice, to aboliſh Epiſcopacy, which had flouriſhed in all ages, and all places of the world, even in <hi>Aethiopia</hi> and <hi>India</hi> (where the Popes Supremacy is diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) from the very Apoſtles days; for pretending to ſtand by the ſame Authority, which their upſtart Model had, againſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171525:18"/>Scripture, and Antiquity, moſt illegally uſurped? How highly did theſe men ſin againſt this Text, abuſe and diſhonour the King, in urging him, with Force and Arms, to pull down that holy Order, which he and his Anceſtors were, at their Coronation, moſt ſolemnly ſworn to preſerve; and which, with all the Priviledges and Liberties of the Church, more than thirty Parliaments had wiſely and maturely confirmed?</p>
            <p>And have they not again attempted, by the Sword, (their only powerful Argument) to compel our preſent Soveraign, contrary to all Rules of Juſtice and Providence, to alter that Government, which has ever been obedient to him, for that which always rebelled againſt him, and turn out a Clergy, who would vindicate his Prerogative, and ſeal their Allegiance with their blood, and place thoſe in their Seats, who were ever diſloyal, and yet claim Authority over him? to whom (as his martyred Father ſaid of them) nothing will give content, but the alteration of the whole frame of the Government, and the total overthrow of Royal Authority:<note place="margin">Decl. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Pacif. at Ber.</note> or, as his Royal Grandfather wrot of them, who will judge and give Law to their King, but be controul'd by none; whom no deſerts can oblige, neither Oaths nor Promiſes bind: breathing nothing but Sedition and Calumnies,<note place="margin">Baſ. Dor.</note> and aſpiring without meaſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This (and much more) was the Character, that wiſe King, who had a long and ſad experience of them, left to his Son: and their many Rebellions ever ſince, ſhew it; not only true of them, who vexed his righteous Soul, but a Prediction of others, who would afterward ſtrictly adhere to their Principles; and in bloody Letters have they, in moſt places ſince, recorded themſelves, the great violaters of this Text.</p>
            <p>But, bleſſed be God, the true Epiſcopal Proteſtants, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways obſerved it, and moſt conſcientiouſly honoured their King; they have adhered to him in the worſt of times, and have been the greateſt preſidents of Fidelity in the world; they have cheerfully ſuffered plundering and ſequeſtration, impriſonment and exile; ſome were Martyrs at Home, and others were Confeſſors abroad; neither Chains, nor Gibbets,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171525:18"/>could terrifie them from their Allegiance; their Religion and Loyalty were grounded on the ſame Foundation, and they could not be Sons of the Church, and Traytors to the King; they muſt lay down old Proteſtancy, when they lift up a hand againſt the Lords Anointed.</p>
            <p>For their Principles are the ſame with thoſe of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, and they will, on no pretence whatſoever, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt their Prince; though he were a Presbyterian, both in Opinion, and Government, they durſt not diſhonour, or diſobey him, but would, with thoſe of old, <hi>flere &amp; mori,</hi> weep and dye, and never draw a Sword againſt him. They would imitate the <hi>Thebean</hi> Legion under <hi>Maximianus,</hi> ſubmit to a ſecond Decimation, and be cut in pieces, before they would ſtrike at their lawful Soveraign. This was, and is ſtill, the Doctrine of our Church, in which ſhe may juſtly triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the World, which we ſhould, at this juncture of time, frequently preach, and defend, with all true Proteſtant Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Reſolution.</p>
            <p>Let us, with the brave <hi>Mauricius,</hi> and <hi>Exuperius,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that Loyal Army, call to our Pariſhioners, <hi>Mori magis quàm vincere,</hi> rather to dye, and fall innocently, than live vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Rebels; let us often ſhew them the eternal Rewards of Fidelity, and the dreadful Puniſhments of Diſobedience;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Ser. againſt Rebel.</note> let us convince them, as 'tis in our Homilies (which alſo ſhews the Doctrine of our Church) that as Heaven is the place of good obedient Subjects, ſo is Hell the Priſon and Dungeon of Rebels againſt God and their Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which allowed Preſident, let us with Loyal and Religious Zeal, cry aloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Breakers of this Text; let us aſſert the Supremacy of Princes in their own Territories, againſt all the Deluſions and Impoſtures of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Geneva;</hi> let us privately diſcourſe them, and publickly preach them, into a devout Reverence, and Loyal Admiration of the preſent Government; which, for the ſecurity of Religion and Property, is moſt certainly the beſt under Heaven; tis eaſie and gentle, not Arbitrary and Tyrannical, and gives the Subject all the Priviledges, he can
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171525:19"/>rationally deſire: no Sequeſtrators or Committy-men are ſeen among us, the Cry of Widdows and Orphans is not heard in our ſtreets; the Peaſant does not groan under Taxes, but every man enjoys his own, and is protected by the Laws, from the Oppreſſions and Injuries of others; for which, and all other Bleſſings we here enjoy, perſwade we our Auditors, to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankful to God and the King, and to expreſs it in all God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Honeſty, in all Loyalty and Affection, in unity and uniformity; and let us in all reſpects, be burning and ſhining Lights unto them: In a word, let us in our Lives and Actions contribute all we can, to the Honour of our King, who is a moſt tender, indulgent and nurſing Father to our Church; Let us ſhew it in our exact Conformity to the Civil and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws, in our great Honour and Obedience to thoſe whom he hath ſet over us, in Church and State, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to him, who for his vaſt abilities, his great Sufferings, and untainted Loyalty, is now moſt deſervedly ſet in the ancient Throne of this Dioceſs; let his Comfort in his Clergy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with his Honour, and let us, by the Holineſs of our Lives, our Conſtancy in Preaching, and other Miniſterial Duties (on which I have formerly on the like occaſion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed) ſhew our Obedience to our Metropolitan, our Fear to God, and Honour to the King.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
